Today's דף סמך, Daf Samech, we pick up a little bit earlier
from נט עמוד ב, Nun Tet Amud Bet, but the entire דף
daf even from where we're starting is all going to be about
אגדתא, Agadeta, so be prepared. Oh, really? Yes. So we start from
the two dots in the middle of נט עמוד ב. Nun Tet
Amud Bet. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. So we had mentioned
before how to distinguish between חיה Chaya and בהמה Behema based on
the hooves and the, oh, excuse me, I don't know if I
did this right, sorry, start that again. Okay, sorry, just to repeat,
we're on נט עמוד ב Nun Tet Amud Bet at the two
dots and we're going to be looking at a lot of אגדתא
Agadeta today, and we start with, and the גמרא Gemara had before
been distinguishing between חיה Chaya and בהמה Behema based on the hooves
and the horn.
And now the גמרא Gemara and had mentioned that there's this one
thing called a קרש Keresh or קרש, Keresh, whatever, that has one
horn in it which nobody really knows and it's כשר, kosher, nobody
exactly knows what that is. Okay, and now let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. So at the two dots, קרש אף על פי
שאין לו אלא קרן אחת מותר, Keresh af al pi she-ein lo
ela keren achat mutar, and this קרש Keresh even though it has
only one horn is permissible.
So what is this קרש? Keresh? אמר רב יהודה קרש טביא דבי
עילאי, Amar Rav Yehuda Keresh Tabya Debei Ilai, קרש Keresh is a
deer from this place called בי עילאי, Bei Ilai, רש"י Rashi says
it was a certain forest. So that's what this קרש Keresh was.
Okay,
תגריס, Tagris, and this thing called a תגריס, Tagris, רש"י Rashi says
he doesn't know what the original context was that תגריס Tagris had
been mentioned, but what is this תגריס? Tagris? אריה דבי עילאי, Arye
Debei Ilai, it is a lion from the place of בי עילאי.
Bei Ilai. Okay, and now we're going to tell a little bit
about this
lion. אמר רב כהנא תשע אמות הוי בין אונא לאונא דאריה דבי
עילאי. Amar Rav Kahana tesha amot havei bein una le-una de-arye debei
ilai. There are nine אמות amot from one ear to the next
ear of the lion of בי עילאי, Bei Ilai, so that would
be about what, about fifteen feet. So clearly, and the rest of
this is going to be about these stories about this lion and
clearly it is some mystical creature. So it raises interesting questions that
once this lion is a mystical creature, why people can't just distinguish
that this קרש Keresh is a mystical creature rather than trying to
actually identify an animal, a כשר kosher animal with one
horn? Right, exactly. But by the קרש Keresh it actually was brought
down in a הלכתי Halakhic context so people try to identify it.
Where did it come from, the lion?
Right, that's what רש"י Rashi says. That's what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י
Rashi says he doesn't know how, רש"י Rashi doesn't know why this
was brought in, like whoever mentioned this thing called a תגריס. Tagris.
Well, we mentioned בי עילאי, Bei Ilai, you know, so once we're
talking about בי עילאי, Bei Ilai, we're talking about other things that
we happen to say are animal, you know, very amazing animals from
this place called בי עילאי, Bei Ilai, from this forest.
Okay, did anyone know where that actually is?
No. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so now
a story about this. Okay, אמר רב יוסף שיתסר אמות הוי משכיה
דטביא דבי עילאי. Amar Rav Yosef shit-sar amot havei mashchei de-tabya debei
ilai.
Now sixteen, but talking about mystical, it says sixteen אמות amot is
the, which is again what, like twenty-four feet,
is the length,
is the skin, the leather of this deer of בי עילאי, Bei
Ilai, which is this קרש Keresh which is this thing with the
one horn. So which is why again, it clearly sounds to be
mystical, although again, the interesting suggestion of the what do you call
it, of the שיחת חולין Sichat Chullin that it was a giraffe.
How long is the neck of a giraffe?
Oh, that's interesting.
So it could be around sixteen אמות? amot? Could be around twenty
feet the neck of a giraffe? Anybody? I don't think it's that
high, I think it's
more like twelve feet.
Somebody, well, how about if you did the neck plus their body
all the way down to their feet? Is the total height of
a giraffe could be around twenty feet or so? Twenty-four, maybe. So
that makes the suggestion of giraffe at least most interesting.
But they say it's a טביא, tabya, so then why are people
saying it's a deer?
Well, you know, how do you describe something? It means you're like,
they take a giraffe for a deer. It's thin, it's horse-like, it's
you know, it's like a deer with a super long neck. Right?
If you had no other context to describe it, what would you
say? If you couldn't use the word giraffe, what would you say
it is? It's an X with a long neck. Leopard. A leopard
with a long neck you would say?
Because it's got the spotted skin kind of.
Oh, I guess if you looked at the spots, right. But if
you looked at the body structure, if you looked at the body
structure, it looks like a horse or a deer with a really
long neck. So that makes that suggestion quite fascinating. What? But they
should have said with no antlers.
But they do have little nubs.
Yeah, they do. They do.
Okay, alright, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
Okay, right,
so are we saying this is a giraffe?
That's what the what do you call it, that's what the שיחת
חולין Sichat Chullin suggests. It's the closest match. Okay, I don't know
what this lion is supposed to be. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Where were we? Okay, so let's see
the גמרא. Gemara. שיתסר אמות הוי משכיה. Shit-sar amot havei mashchei. שיתסר
אמות, Shit-sar amot, sixteen אמות, amot, הוי משכיה. havei mashchei. משכיה Mashchei
could mean the leather, but I just checked רש"י Rashi again, he
says here it means the length. Is the length of the טביא
דבי עילאי. Tabya Debei Ilai. So again, so that would be about
twenty-four feet is the length of this animal. Okay, but now... Back
to the lion. אמר ליה amlei, קיסר לרבי יהושע *Amar lei keisar
l'Rabbi Yehoshua*. So now we're gonna have a couple of exchanges between
the Caesar, thank you, and רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*. So the Caesar
says to רבי יהושע בן חנניה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya, *Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Chananya*. אלוקיכם כאריה מתיל *Eloheichem k'aryeh masil*. Your God is compared
to a lion. Now the theme of all of these exchanges is
going to be that the Roman Caesar believes in many gods, but
also obviously believes in a greater
anthropomorphic physical sense of gods, and therefore is going to take our
understanding of God in his terms. So therefore he's going to treat
this fact that he's about to quote a lion where God is
compared to the roaring of a lion and treat it very literally.
So let's take a look. So he said to רבי יהושע בן
חנניה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya. *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya*.
He said the following: אלוקיכם כאריה
מתיל *Eloheichem k'aryeh masil*.
Your God is, the word מתיל *masil* is like משל *mashal*. Your
God is compared to a lion, דכתיב Dechtiv, *d'chesiv*, אריה שאג מי
לא יירא *Aryeh shaag mi lo yira*. A lion will roar, who
shall not fear. And the end of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is
ה׳ אלוקים דיבר מי לא ינבא *Hashem Elokim diber mi lo yinavei*.
If the Lord God speaks, who will not prophesy? So therefore God's
speaking is like the roaring of a lion. Now where the context
it means that it can't be resisted. Okay, but nevertheless, מאי רבותיה
Mai revuseih, *Mai revusei*? So the Caesar said to רבי יהושע בן
חנניה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Hananya? *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya*, what's the חידוש
*chiddush*? What's the big deal? פרשא קטיל אריה *Parasha katil aryeh*. A
horseman can kill a lion. So what if your God is like
a lion? Big deal. So, now by the way, God was not
compared to a lion, but the roar was compared, but anyway. All
right, אמר ליה amlei, *Amar lei*, so he said, no, לא כהאי
אריה מתיל *lo k'hai aryeh masil*. Not like that type of a
lion. כאריה דבי עילאי מתיל *K'aryeh d'Bei Ilai masil*. He was compared
to the lion of בי עילאי *Bei Ilai* which is obviously just
an amazing lion,
which nobody could resist. אמר ליה amlei, *Amar lei*, so the Caesar
said, בעינא דמחזית לי ניהליה *beina d'machzis li nihalei*. I want you
to show him to me, this lion. אמר ליה amlei, *Amar lei*,
לא מצי חזית ליה *lo matzi chazis lei*. You can't see this
lion. This lion is too wondrous, it's too whatever, it's also too
hidden. It's impossible to see it. אמר ליה amlei, *Amar lei*, all
right, from מסורא *Mesora*? אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar lei*, איברא חזינא
ליה ivra chazina lei, *ivra chazina lei*. No, in truth I will
see him. You know, the Caesar says, talk about ה׳ אלוקים דיבר
מי לא ינבא *Hashem Elokim diber mi lo yinavei*. The Caesar says
he's gonna see him, he's gonna see him. What did איברא ivera,
*ivra* mean?
איברא *ivra* like
in truth, like no, in truth I will see him. He said,
tough luck, I'm going to see him. You make it happen. Okay,
so בעי רחמי rachamei, *bei rachamei*. So רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*
prayed to God to help make this happen. איתעקר מדוכתיה *Is'akar miduchsei*.
The lion got uprooted from its place, meaning left this forest. כי
הוה מרחיק ארבע מאה פרסי *Ki havei marchik arba mea parsei*.
When he was 400 פרסי *parsei* away from his home, this lion,
נהם חד קלא *neham chad kala*. He roared one roar and אפילו
כל מעברתא *apilu kol me'avarta*, every pregnant woman in hearing distance miscarried,
ושורא דרומי d'Romi. נפל *v'shura d'Romi nafal*, and the walls of Rome
fell down. Okay, so that's ה׳ אלוקים דיבר מי לא ינבא *Hashem
Elokim diber mi lo yinavei*. So you see what the roar of
this lion is like.
Okay, so what happened? We're not done. כי אמרחיק תלת מאה פרסי
*Ki amarchik tlas mea parsei*. He went another 300 פרסי *parsei* from
his home, this lion. נהם קלא אחרינא *Neham kala achrina*. And he
gave out another roar. נתור כיכי ושיני דגברי *Natur kichei v'shinei d'gavrei*.
So all of the molars and incisors of people, of men, fell
out. ואף הוא נפל מכורסיה לארעא *V'af hu nafal michurseia l'ara*. And
even the Caesar fell off of his seat to the ground. Okay,
so he fell down to the ground. אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar
lei*, so the Caesar then said back to רבי יהושע בן חנניה
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Hananya *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya*, במטותא
מינך *b'matusa minach*, by your plea basically, בעי רחמי rachamei עליה דלהדר
לדוכתיה *bei rachamei alei d'lihadar l'duchsei*. Pray that the lion should return
to its place. בעי רחמי עליה והדר לדוכתיה *Bei rachamei alei v'hadar
l'duchsei*. So רבי יהושע בן חנניה Yehoshua ben Hananya *Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Chananya* prayed for the lion and the lion returned to its place.
So he understood that when God is compared to a lion and
now we see that this clearly is a very
mystical figure, figure, not animal here. But anyway, he understood that
it was a very awesome comparison. It was comparing God to something
that was very awesome. You know, it might also be related to
the fact that the Romans, when they after they won their various
battles and war in these exotic places brought back these exotic animals.
Oh, there's you got a giraffe. How big is a giraffe?
Their legs are over six feet.
Oh wow.
So they probably are more than,
they chew their cud.
Yeah, right, exactly.
Standing up and their babies drop five feet to the ground.
Oh wow, right. Within ten hours they're running with their mothers and
okay. But what's their total, what's their height? Is their height about
שיתסר אמות *shitsar amos*? Probably if their legs are five or six
feet.
I'm trying to find out how long their neck is.
Let's
just look at their total height.
How many feet is שיתסר אמות *shitsar amos*?
שיתסר אמות *Shitsar amos* about twenty-four. An אמה *amah* is about a
foot and a half. So anyway, so you know the Romans brought
back these exotic animals to parade in Rome after they had the,
after they won. after they won these battles in these foreign and
exotic locations. So maybe that's also part of the subtext here, like
you saying lions? Big deal. Like you know, we have lions, we
bring lions to our you know Colosseums and whatever, God is a
lion? Big deal. So one said oh no, there are some animals
that still are able to strike awe even to, you know, even
even to the Romans. So that would be this this sort of
this this lion. All right, so moving on.
Yoyie, do you have, eighteen, two thousand four hundred to four thousand
pounds and stand up to nineteen feet?
Nineteen feet, okay. Ah, so pretty close. All right. All right. So
anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So that's about
this lion. Now, אמר ליה קיסר לרבי יהושע בן חנניה amlei keisar
lerabbi yehoshua ben chananya another story. The Caesar said to רבי יהושע
בן חנניה, Yehoshua ben Hananya? בעינא דאיחזי ליה לאלוקיכו, be'ina de'ichzei lei
le'elokeichu, I want to see your God. Okay, again, you know, very
much in the in the pagan perspective that something that can be
seen, so I want to see your God. So אמר ליה, Amar
lei, לא מצית חזית ליה, lo matzis chazis lei, you can't see
him. לא יראני האדם וחי. lo yirani ha'adam vachai. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, איברא חזינא ליה, in truth I will see him, make it
happen. So אזל אוקמיה לאפיתא דשמיא מעלי האי יומא azal okmei leapta
deshamai ma'ale hachai yoma
he took the Caesar and made him stand in the presence of
the sun. יומא yoma is interesting in Aramaic it can mean the
sun, יום, yom, day, sun. Anyway, בתקופת תמוז bitkufas tammuz in the
middle of the summer. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אסתכל ביה, istakeil bei,
said look straight at the sun. אמר ליה, Amar lei, לא מצינא,
lo matzina, I can't, it's like you know, hurt my eyes, I
can't look straight at the sun, I can't see it with this
light. אמר ליה, Amar lei, יומא דחד משמשיה דקאי קמי קודשא בריך
הוא, yoma dechad mishamshei deka'i kamei kudesha berich hu, the sun which
is just one of the servants that stands before God, who אמרת
לא מצינא לאסתכולי ביה, amart lo matzina l'istakulei bei, you can't see
him, שכינה Shechinah לא כל שכן, lo kol sheken, how much more
so can you not see the actual presence of God. Now, the
מהרש"א Maharsha I think, I forget, I looked both at the מהרש"א
Maharsha and the מהר"ל Maharal for what their comments on this אגדתא
aggadetah but I think it was the מהרש"א Maharsha but the מהרש"א
Maharsha said that the point is is that you know that the
sun is light and it's something like almost it's something that's the
least physical of the parts of our physical world is light. So
therefore and the point was was that if you can't directly see
the light itself, meaning we would say you can't see the sun
because it's so hot, you know whatever so bright. But he said
that the point was more because of its lack of physicality. It's
it's just light and you can't see light itself. So how much
more so can you not see God which is even more removed
from the physical world? So you know, so which is I mean
I think nice because it's getting more to the core of the
argument. It's not just saying hi you can't see the sun so
you can't see God. Saying the reason you can't see it is
because it's you know it's not it's not physical, it's just light,
so how much more so can you not see
God which is even more removed from the physical world. Because you
can't just take an ounce of dark either. It can't, yeah. What
are you looking at? Like, see where dark is coming from.
Yeah, but I don't see the point. Here the point was if
you can't see one of the things that God created or one
of the servants of God, how do you think you can see
God? So, you know, in the simple sense here it's just like
it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer but it really doesn't get to
the heart of the problem, right? So oh look you can't see
the sun so you can't see God.
Right?
You can't see wind.
So right, you could have you know, but actually that might have
been a similar point. It's actually interesting, I wonder why he didn't
say that. But you know but also the idea that light represents
you know like you know light is very much also compared to
God, you know the sense of like you know metaphorically. Right. So
there is a power to this whole to to you know to
this argument you know sort of getting a little bit closer to
the core of the response. Okay.
How common is the term שכינה Shechinah used in the?
That's a good question. I think not infrequently. I'd have to check
but I don't think not infrequently. You know, it's not used in
the תורה Torah at all. תנ"ך. Tanach. תנ"ך, Tanach, it's used as
a verb, that God is שוכן, shochein, right.
But they say הקדוש ברוך
הוא.
Hakadosh
Baruch Hu.
Right. Why did they shift to שכינה? Shechinah? Yeah, that's a good
question, why they shift to שכינה Shechinah rather than just saying... Maybe
because שכינה Shechinah again is the sense of God's presence in this
world, so if there was anything you could see, it would be
the שכינה. Shechinah.
Okay.
All right. So אמר ליה קיסר לרבי יהושע בן חנניה. amlei keisar
lerabbi yehoshua ben chananya. So now he said to רבי יהושע בן
חנניה. Yehoshua ben Hananya So he dealt with the impossibility to see
God, we dealt with sort of the how you know the comparison
of God to a lion, with a meaningful comparison. Now let's see
what he says. So he says בעינא דאעביד ליה נהמא לאלוהיכם. be'ina
de'aeivid lei nahama le'eloheichem.
I want to prepare bread, prepare a banquet for your God. Okay?
So which is actually and again I think it's I forget who
it is that says this, I think it was some מהר"ל, Maharal,
he said you know you sort of understand what he's trying to
do is he's trying to put the Jewish God in some type
of a pagan context. So you know I'm not exactly sure how
the lion thing fits in but certainly the idea of being able
to see Him and then okay even if I accept that He
can't be seen but at least the idea of feeding God, you
know they fed their gods and we actually you know the קרבן
korban is you know ריח ניחוח, reiach nichoach, you know it's לחם
אשי lechem ishei you know it's לחם אשי lechem ishei the bread
the fire offering and so on, except the point again being that
we take that very metaphorically and they take it more literally you
know about the god being fed. So even if it's true that
I can't see your God and relate to your God and can't
be so whatever but I mean I can't see your God but
at least I should be able to treat Him like a pagan
god to feed Him, that aspect should still be accurate so you
know should still
should still be relevant. So let's take a look.
So where were we? אמר ליה לא מצי. Amar lei lo matzi.
You can't. אמאי? Amai? Why not? He says נפישי חילואתיה nefishi chilvosei
because his troops are so numerous that you can't even feed his
troops let alone feeding God. So again trying to answer him within
his own mindset not trying to point out that it's completely irrelevant
to our understanding of God. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so the Caesar
said back איברא, in truth I will. אמר ליה, Amar Lei I
will feed him. So I will make a banquet for him. אמר
ליה, Amar leh, he says to him פוק צביס לגידא דרביסא, puk
tzvis l'gida d'Revisa, go to the banks of this river called the
Revisa דרווח עלמא, deravich alma,
it's you know very wide open space and prepare your banquet for
him there. So טרח שיתא ירחי, tarach shita yarchei, he worked for
six months to prepare the banquet of קייטא kayta of the summer,
קיץ. kayitz. אתא זיקא, asa zika, so then came a wind which
Rashi says was the plan all along of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Hananya.
אתא זיקא, asa zika, כנשינהו לימא kanshenhu l'yama and it sort of
swept it into the
sea or the river whatever. So טרח שיתא ירחי דסתווא tarach shita
yarchei d'sitva and then he prepared a banquet, he spent the next
six months of the winter preparing the banquet. אתא מיטרא asa mitra
came the rain. סתווא sitva is really like fall slash winter. Anyway
it includes the rainy season, right? Right. I know but the Gemara
really talks about primarily two seasons קייטא kayta and סתווא. sitva. So
קייטא kayta is like spring summer and סתווא sitva is like fall
winter, okay? What? Rainy season and dry season, right, exactly.
So came the rain אתא מיטרא, asa mitra, טבעיה בימא tavyei b'yama
and again washed it into the sea.
אמר ליה, so the Caesar went back and he said מאי האי,
mai hai, what's going on? אמר ליה, הני כנושאי וזלוחאי דאתו קמיה,
hani knushai v'zulchai d'asu kamei, these are the sweepers and the dusters
and the sprinklers that go before God's troops. Like you know because
you would sweep up a place and it looks clean and they
would put water on it to settle the dust. So the wind
and the rain are the sweepers and the dusters that go before
God. These are just the sweepers and the dusters, we haven't even
gotten to all the attendants.
So אמר ליה, so he said I'm sorry אמר ליה, אי הכי
לא מצצינא, i hachi lo matzina, oh then I certainly won't be
able to actually make a banquet for God if even these like
sweepers and dusters take six, a year's worth of the food and
sweep it away. Okay so
again it's a little bit hard to understand you know how this
is getting to the substance of the point you know again unless
the point is that you know because the real point is that
God isn't physical and the whole idea of feeding God is irrelevant
and it's hard to see you know it's hard to see how
this sort of got to the core argument but at least it
was sort of pointing out to him the absurdity of it. If
you you know once we recognize that everything in the world is
from
God then you know then if you can't make things to to
address all of these natural forces in the world then how much
less so can you do anything that's meaningful in terms of giving
food to God. But it seems to be some deeper argument here
that I'm missing.
But what I'm actually missing to get back to where this whole
thing started from is so they're making a ruling about a mythical
animal?
Well that's what I said before. I said the stories about the
lion seems to make it all mythical so maybe it raises the
whole question about a, should we try to identify this animal this
one horn that the Gemara is talking about or just assume that
it was mythical and ignore it. You know I think that it's
possible that it was mythical but if you you know you know
the way things that are mythical like the I bet if you
took a poll I was going to say you take a poll
of Americans how many people actually believe there's such a thing as
a unicorn? Right I'm sure that it is a non-insignificant percentage of
people actually believe that a unicorn exists. Right and so you sometimes
things are so mythical that you actually start believing that they exist
so I don't think it's impossible that there was a mythical
one-horned חיה chaya out there you know belief in this thing that
the Gemara believed existed so it said here would be the ruling
about it it would be kosher. All right but because people are
troubled with how do you have a ruling about something that's not
really exist they try to identify it and the giraffe is not
a bad guess.
Did they categorize a שור הבר? shor habor?
Yeah that's an interesting question. Well it says that the שור הבר
shor habor will be eaten in the סעודה לעתיד לבוא seuda l'asid
lavo so clearly that's kosher, right? Yes.
They also had a one-horned deer as a unicorn. But there isn't
a real one-horned deer that they had seen. Really? You know when
you think about life there are children that are born with two
I mean anything can exist right? It can be an aberration in
nature but the animal itself chews its cud so technically right right.
Right but I mean but the question is that are we talking
actually that there is such a species or at least an aberration.
But it doesn't do anything it's not like the שור הבר shor
habor for לעתיד לבוא l'asid lavo or לויתן. livyasan. It's just this
animal? Right. And is there more than one of them?
I don't know it does not sound like that. Okay so now
we go on at least there's not more than one of these
lions. Okay so אמר ליה, what? Yeah exactly.
All right so now we have... Okay so אמר ליה okay right
exactly.
All right so now we have these arguments about you know trying
to make our God like their gods and the responses being you
know whatever it is that it's you know it's of a completely
different category and you cannot and you cannot try to fit our
God into your box.
So now יהושע בן חנניה Yehoshua ben Hananya lived in the time
of the
מקדש?
Mikdash? Yeah only which Caesar this was.
So then why didn't he just tell him bring a קרבן? Korban?
Why instead did he?
Well you see that's the interesting thing which is how does how
is
what he said I want to make prepare a feast how is
that different you know he
used the word
לחמא Lachma bread which is the word in the Torah which is
אשה Isheh right how is that really different than you know than
the whole concept of קרבנות? Korbanot? What did he say that reflected
meaning here's my point what did he say that reflected a pagan
theology in what in his question more than you know a concept
of
קרבנות? Korbanot? Maybe it was because he used the word I want
to arrange a banquet or you know maybe it's just like similar
to the lion question maybe it's just that he took you know
what we consider to be metaphorical and he took it literal.
You know so what the physicality?
Right meaning but you know we also say לחם אשה Lechem Isheh
and etc. but you know maybe that's the whole point that maybe
it was similar to the point about seeing God. You know when
the Torah says לא יראני האדם וחי Lo Yerani Ha'adam Vachai we
often immediately translate that not translate but sort of you know interpret
that process that as oh God is abstract God is not physical.
But that's not literally what the Torah says. It says God you
know God's not that God is not is not is not is
not meaning
you can't see Him because the result of seeing Him will kill
you but not because God fundamentally is not able to be seen.
But we interpret it as saying no no no you know I
mean like it's the רמב"ם Rambam the way based on the רמב"ם's
Rambam whole you know emphasis about rejecting all the anthropomorphisms in the
Torah of having any literal sense right including this it's every time
the Torah uses those terminologies we automatically say those are all just
metaphors. And what it really means is that there's no physicality to
God and God can't be seen and you know etc. etc. But
again the simple sense of the פסוקים Psukim are not that way.
So in a way what he's asking is you could say it's
taking what the Torah says הרי ישאג Harei Yishag לא יראני האדם
Lo Yerani Ha'adam right and you know and whatever and לחם אשה
Lechem Isheh and just translating it more literally and more the context
of a pagan context and you know much more in a sense
of a physical God rather than the way we translate all these
things which is much more metaphorically. So that is the consistent theme
here between these three cases. Okay Rabbi Yehoshua yeah he lived at
this time.
Yeah I understand let me
tell you he was the Yehoshua that the
Roman emperor right right right. Well you always have to wonder in
general about the stories with you know with the rabbis talking to
the supreme leaders of the civilized world you know whether these things
whether these stories actually happened or not. I am not finding how
could I not find a רבי יהושע בן חנניה? Hananya When I
am looking in the right place
I am not seeing a רבי יהושע בן חנניה here. I would
have to look at it. But maybe he was not a major
figure.
We have חנניה בן תרדיון Hananya ben Teradyon so maybe he was
just Hananya the son?
Could could be.
I am have to somebody could look it up he is not
here. I don't know how frequent he is but he's not here.
Okay he could cer-
does your Steinsaltz have any biographical reference?
יהושע בן חנניה?
No?
I can try checking on my new reference work is Hebrew Wikipedia
which I can even get on my droid.
There is Hebrew Wikipedia? The Hebrew Wikipedia is great because it's written
by all these Israeli academics.
And
it's in Hebrew. Oh great.
On the regular Wikipedia site you just hit Hebrew?
I don't know I type in ויקיפדיה Vikipedia in my Hebrew font
and I get it. ויקיפדיה? Vikipedia? In Hebrew font?
Yeah in other languages too.
Yeah
יהושע בן חנניה
חנניה let's see what we get.
Wikipedia in English.
Well we have to translate the Hebrew Wikipedia. יהושע בן חנניה ויקיפדיה
Vikipedia okay here we go.
דור שני לתנאים Dor Sheni L'Tanna'im
he
was the student of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai
his colleagues were רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel of יבנה Yavneh whatever
his students were רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael etc.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai introduced him to the Caesar.
So so
it's immediately post חורבן Churban I mean רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai you know was like the was the
transition was at the time of the חורבן. Churban. Okay all right
so now we can right
we can even get that historic context so he's saying now you
don't have a temple
right right that's a good point yeah that's a nice point. All
right so
okay where are we?
Okay אמר ליה בת קיסר לרבי יהושע Amar lei bat Keisar l'Rabbi
Yehoshua the daughter of the Caesar said to Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya.
Now that he was done with his exchanges with the Caesar, now
he's talking to the daughter of the Caesar. And also, you know,
again, sort of treats things very literally. אלהיכם נגרא הוא, Eloheichem nagra
hu, your God is a carpenter. דכתיב, Dechtiv,
yes, interesting, right, we know of other religions that had carpenters related
to their gods. Okay. Anyway, your God is a carpenter. I know,
דכתיב, de-chtiv, as the verse says, המקרה במים עליותיו, Hamakareh bamayim aliyotav,
God spreads over the water his, you know, his chambers, his, you
know,
his stories. So, you see that he built his heavens over the
waters, so he's a carpenter. Now, again, somebody says that the point
here is to argue that he did not create the world יש
מאין yesh me’ayin out of nothing, but he had materials there and
he worked with the material that he had, you know, there’s like
a famous phrase in בראשית רבה Bereishis Rabbah where it says, oh,
well of course your God could create the world because he had
all these good materials to start with. He had the חושך choshech
and the אור or and the מים, mayim, you know, because it
said, you know, והמים היתה, v’hamayim haysa, you know, שמים וארץ, shamayim
v’aretz, והארץ היתה תהו ובהו. v’ha'aretz haysa tohu vavohu.
He had the תהו tohu and the בהו vohu and the חושך
choshech because it never says God created those things. It just, you
know, said שמים וארץ, shamayim v’aretz, but it doesn’t say specifically. So
that’s like an old argument that who says that the פסוקים pesukim
are so clear that they came out of nothing? So your God—so
that’s an interesting sort of subtext. Anyway, so your God—or possible read,
your God is a carpenter. So, in that light, I take this
joke, which is
these people were arguing about what is the first profession in the
world. So the surgeon says, oh, well of course surgery, because you
know when God did surgery on אדם Adam to make חוה. Chava.
And then somebody said, no, no, no,
it's—I'm trying to forget, there are a couple of professions that have
their say, but anyway after a couple then, you know, the engineer
says or whatever if you want the carpenter says, you know, oh,
you know, it's engineering or it's carpentry, it's construction, you know, because
when God created the world. And the lawyer says, one minute, who
do you think made the תהו ובהו? tohu vavohu? All right, whatever,
dum da dum. Anyway, moving on. There’s got to be a better
way to deliver that punchline. Okay, so moving on. And my apologies
to
all the lawyers out there. All right, anyway, so now we go
on. Anyway, so your God is a carpenter. אמר ליה, tell your
God דנעביד לי חדא מסטוריסא d'na'avid li chada mistorisa to make me
a spool, a tiny little thing, just a little spool of thread.
Let’s see really if, you know, what your God can do. So
if he can really do the types of things that he's claimed
to do. אמר לחיי, Amar lachai, he says, you know, be it
let it be so. So,
as opposed to the Caesar that actually he resisted, here he said
let it be so, maybe because he felt that she was sort
of like mocking or testing, you know, God.
She wasn't like doing נסיונות nisyonos to, you know, השם. Hashem.
He was being challenged by the Caesar, what do you want? בעי
רחמי עלה, Bei rachamei aleh, he prayed, he prayed for her. Now
it's interesting because the phrase רחמי, you know, is the classic phrase
used in the גמרא Gemara for prayer,
רחמי מיניה, rachamei minei, רחמי מיניה. rachamei minei. But here, it means
he prayed for her. But as we're going to see in the
story, it's not necessarily something compassionate. It's actually he prayed to deal
with this case, but it didn't like before by the lion, it
wasn't really helping anybody. The word רחמי means prayer but not necessarily
with the impact of רחמים. rachamim. So let’s see. He prayed for
her, ואינגע, v'inga, and she got leprosy. אותבה בשוקא דרומי, Osvah b’shuka
d’Romi,
so she was sat in the marketplace of Rome,
יהבו לה מסטוריסא, yahvu lah mistorisa, and they gave her a spool,
which is what she said, let your God make for me a
spool. Why? A thread? דהכי הוה נהיגי, De’hachi hava nehigi, because the
practice was דכל דמינגע ברומי, de’chol d’minga b’Romi, anybody who had leprosy
in Rome, יהבו לה מסטוריסא, yahvu lah mistorisa, they would give him
a spool, ויתיב בשוקא, v’yasiv b’shuka, and he would sit in the
marketplace, וסתר דוללי, v'sasir dolalay, and would sort of wrap around its
thread, כי היכי דליחזו אינשי, ki heichi d'lichzei inshi, that people would
see, I don't know what this has to do why it's specific
to leprosy unless this was just, you know, whatever was associated the
symbolism, and people would see, וליבעי רחמי עליה, v’liv'ei rachamei aleih, they'd
know this person would have leprosy and they'd pray for the person.
So therefore, you said let your God make me a spool. Yes,
but this is not the Torah's leprosy. This is the, you know,
medical leprosy.
This medical condition. Well, if that's contagious?
Well, I don't know if they knew that.
I mean,
people—so, I mean, you know, there's always the stories about the lepers
in the streets of, you know, Jerusalem and in the streets of
Rome and so yeah, they would go around and they would beg
and they would yell.
And they
would yell.
Right, exactly.
Or they'd scream so people would stay away from them.
That's the Torah's צרעת. tzara’as. That I
not—not this, which is just the medical condition of leprosy. Okay, so
anyway, so she wanted—she wanted a spool, she got her spool. Okay.
חד יומא הוה קחליף התם, Chad yoma hava kachalif hatam,
so one day
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya was passing through there, הוה יתבה וסתרה דוללי
בשוקא, hava yasvah v'sasra dolalay b'shuka, and there she was in the
marketplace, you know, doing the rowing her spool of thread דרומי. אמר
לה, Amar lah, so he said to her, שפירתא מסטוריסא דיהב לך
אלהיך, Shapirta mistorisa d'yahav lach Elohayich, is it a beautiful spool that
your God gave you? Are you happy with the, with the spool
that my God has given you? So, pretty, he's, that's pretty risky
to be talking to the daughter of the Caesar that way. אמרה
ליה, Amra leh, she said to him, אימא ליה לאלהך לישקול מאי
דיהב לי, Eima leh l'Elach lishkol mai deyahav li, ask your God
to take back what he has given me. So אמר לה, Amar
la, he said to her, אלהא דידן מיהב יהיב משקל לא שקיל,
Elaha didan mehav yahiv mishkal lo shakil, our God gives but doesn't
take back. Our God is no Indian giver. So he gave you
this gift, he's not taking back. Of course he made the lion
go back, but alright. So I don't know what to do with
this story. This is becoming a little more bizarre. The other ones
you've got the basic point that it was about the pagan theology,
you know,
grappling with the Jewish concept of God. But here I'm not sure
what the, you know, what the point is unless, unless she was
sort of mocking and testing. So the point is, right, so she
got and it was a very different type of a question and
challenge than the Caesar's was. Alright. Okay. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav
Yehuda, now that now we're moving on to other related aggadic statements.
Now we had discussed, you know, about what the lion looks like
and this and this other thing looks like, כרש, keresh, let's take
a look. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, שור, shor, an ox,
כרסתן, karsetan, has a very wide stomach,
ופרסתן, ufarsatan, and wide hoofs, רב רישיה, rav reishia, and a big
head, ורב גנובתיה, verav genovteih, and a big tail. That's an ox.
וחילופא
בחמרא, Vechilufa bechamra, and donkeys are different, that they have, you know,
thin, they're thin-bodied, they're thin hoofs, small tails, and small heads. Okay,
so the Gemara says, למאי נפקא מינה, Lemai nafka mina, why do
I why do I care about this? No, you said also why
we're talking about it here. No, it's fine. Anyway, why why right,
why you talking about this? למקח וממכר, Lemekach umimkar, for business. Now
what does it mean for business? Normally for business means like you'll
tell somebody, you know, you know, if you made a deal and
and you didn't get what you had stipulated for, you should know
that this is normally what's included and so on. Here, if I'm
buying an ox, I'm getting an ox. I mean, people do know
what an ox is and what a donkey is. What diff what
what right, what does it matter that you've given me, so Rashi
says it means less to sort of challenge a deal but more
to like to give buyer's advice. If you're out in the market
looking for ox or looking for donkeys, you should know that these
are the classic characteristics and if it doesn't have these then something
is off and something is wrong.
So if you so if you sold me a donkey with a
whatever, a short long whatever it was, the opposite then I can
say, oh, you sold me you sold me a.
Yeah, so it never it never goes so far to claim that
it's a type of a מקח טעות, mekach taut, but it's more
just like good, good advice of what to look for.
Or if he was buying the ox tail for their soup, so
if it's a small tail you know it's a donkey tail.
Could be. Alright oh that's interesting. You mean if they're selling the
parts separately. So that's interesting. Okay. I don't know what the exact
נפקא מינה nafka mina would be. But that's always the Gemara's answer.
Like if it's something that does has to do with the physical
world where we don't understand what the relevant halakhic context is, somehow
in the world of commerce it's going to be relevant to know
that this is how this is how things work in the world
and this is what things look like in the world. Okay. Okay.
ואמר רב יהודה, Ve'amar Rav Yehuda, so Rav Yehuda said, שור, shor,
so now we're getting back into aggadic statements but this is the
same Rav Yehuda, שור שהקריב אדם הראשון, shor shehikriv Adam HaRishon, an
ox
that the first man offered up, presumably this is within the context
of after he realized he had sinned and God confronted him he
offered up a קרבן korban to God.
Just a conjecture he did that.
Yes, במדרש. bamidrash. Okay, so right, right, so קרן אחת היתה לו,
keren achat hayeta lo, and this is obviously picking up on the
theme of this כרש, keresh, so this horn had one horn, this
ox had one horn במצחו bemitzcho on its head, שנאמר, shene'emar, ותיטב
להשם משור פר מקרין מפריס, Vetitav l'Hashem mishor par makrin mafris, it
shall be as good to God as the ox as the ox
מקרין מפריס makrin mafris with the horns and the hoofs. So the
Gemara says, מאי מקרין, mai makrin, horns with a יוד? yud? תרתי
משמע, tarti mashma, implies two horns. So אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav
Nachman, מקרן כתיב, mikeren ketiv, no it's written without the יוד yud
so it means that this ox, this פסוק pasuk is read to
be in the context of Adam HaRishon's offering קרבן korban to God,
which again is not in the פסוקים, pesukim, in the מדרש, midrash,
that it's read with so therefore it says
one horn. ואמר רב יהודה, Ve'amar Rav Yehuda, and Rav Yehuda also
said, שור שהקריב אדם הראשון, shor shehikriv Adam HaRishon, the ox that
was brought by Adam HaRishon, קרניו קדמו לפרסותיו, karnav kadmu lefarsotav, the
horn preceded the hoofs. Now what does this mean? It means that
a normal animal that's born is born without the horn, but it
is born with the hoofs, and the horn only comes later in
life. This animal was born, the horn preceded. Why? Says the פסוק
passuk says ותיטב להשם משור פר מקרין מפריס. Vetitav l'Hashem mishor par
makrin mafris. So again this ox is מקרין מפריס makrin mafris with
hoofs and horns, מקרין ברישא, makrin bereisha, first horns והדר מפריס, vehadar
mafris, and then and then hoofs. Now what's the meaning of that?
So מסייע ליה לרבי יהושע בן לוי, mesaye leh l'Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, this comes to support Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, דאמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי, de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, for Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
said, כל מעשה בראשית, kol ma'aseh bereishit, all the acts
of creation, בקומתן נבראו
לדעתן נבראו בצביונם נבראו, bekomatan nivre'u l'da'atan nivre'u betzivyonam nivre'u, were built
in their full stature with their
either with their knowledge or to or to their knowledge with their
beauty. According to their will and according to their pleasure. Now what
does that mean? So full stature means, it's
like exactly, like Adam was not created as a fetus or as
a baby, he was created as a full grown, so an ox
also was created as full grown. So that's what it means that
the hoofs did not precede the horn, because it was created with
the hoofs and the horn together. Now what does it mean the
horn preceded? It might not literally mean the horn preceded, it might
just mean the hoofs didn't precede, but it also might mean רש"י
Rashi says like maybe the animal rose from the ground. So if
it rose straight out of the ground, since it was in an
upright position, the horn would have come out before the hoofs. So
that's in their full stature. The other two is interesting what they
mean. בדעתן, be-da'atan,
רש"י Rashi explains it to mean לדעתן, le-da'atan, as if God asked
the animal or whatever, the angels over the animals like, 'do you
agree to be created in this form?' or 'do you want to
be created?' or something of that nature. But more simply it means
with their intellect meaning with their developed brain. So to say they
weren't created with an infant brain, they were created with an adult
brain and maybe by the animals you could say, the whole question
by animals is, where did their instincts come from?
So they were created with all of those instincts that,
if the animals were created out of nothing, how did they develop
their natural instincts? So those were
already put in them from the beginning.
כל מעשה בראשית kol ma'aseh bereishit though, means also the trees though.
Yeah, but they're talking about more the live animals. And בצביונן, be-tzivyonan,
and now צביונן tzivyonan can mean, again, רש"י Rashi says that it
means their pleasure, which makes it then hard to know exactly how
they're so different from לדעתן. le-da'atan. He says it's like a דמות,
demut, right? So בצביונן be-tzivyonan as the form. Michael, give
me a break. Okay, anyway, according to their again, either desire or
pleasure, or it could also mean צביונן tzivyonan like their glory, they
had their
full appearance on them to them. So which is again not exactly
clear how different that is from their full form, if that's what
it means. Okay. But when רש"י Rashi says here, thank you Michael,
לצביונן בדמותן שבחרו להם, le-tzivyonan be-dmutan she-bacharu lahem,
it sounds like he's working from the word, not the word דמות,
demut, צביונן tzivyonan not defining דמות, demut, but צביונן tzivyonan defining desire,
they chose this appearance. Okay, so but then again, it's not exactly
clear how that's different than לדעתן. le-da'atan. Anyway, שנאמר shene'emar as the
verse says, ויכלו השמים והארץ וכל צבאם, vayechulu hashamayim ve-ha'aretz ve-chol tzeva'am,
אל תקרי צבאם, al tikrei tzeva'am, don't read all of its hosts,
אלא צביונן, ela tzivyonan,
their desire. Now
the מהרש"ל Maharshal says or again somebody says that it's a triple
play on the word, תוספות Tosafot quotes part of this in the
name of the הלכות גדולות Halachot Gedolot I think, of the ערוך,
Arukh, a triple play on the word
צבי. tzvi. צבי tzvi can mean
glory, like צבי הוא לכל הארצות, tzvi hu le-chol ha-aratzot, right? And
beauty, ולצבי ולתפארת, u-ltzvi u-letifaret, right?
צבי tzave is Aramaic for desire,
and and I forget what the third one is. Yeah, anyway, somehow
they're all plays, possible plays on the word צבי. tzvi. Fine, anyway,
דרש רבי חנינא בר פפא. darash Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa. רבי חנינא
בר פפא Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa explained יהי כבוד ה' לעולם ישמח
ה' במעשיו. yehi chevod Hashem le-olam yismach Hashem be-ma'asav. So now that
we're talking about the animals being created and fully formed and that
it was with their acquiescence or desire, we're going to continue on
that theme. So what does the פסוק pasuk that says 'God's glory
shall be forever, God will be happy with His creatures'. פסוק זה
שר העולם אמרו. passuk zeh sar ha-olam amro.
This verse was said by the שר sar of the world. Not
the King of the world, the שר, sar, the officer over the
world, which is a number of the commentators say that this is
going to this חז"ל's Chazal idea of this angel called מטטרון, Metatron,
which is sort of seen to be the God's second hand man
as it were. The person that, the angel that is appointed with
the charge of seeing over to the affairs of the world.
So I said second hand man, sorry, second hand angel.
I was using that as an idiomatic expression.
Can I ask a question?
No. Enough. We gotta make some progress. So anyway, which is obviously
a very, an idea that we don't, that I think a lot
of us find very
uncomfortable because the whole way in which that angels is one thing,
because at least angels in the תורה Torah are very seen as
very distant from God, very much like these tiny little messengers. But
to have to believe in this whole idea of angels with this
degree of authority or whatever, I think for many of us is
very, is disturbing in terms of this about a strong monotheistic perspective
on things. But nevertheless, at least the
גמרא Gemara has these, this pops up in the גמרא Gemara from
time to time. So let's take a look. So this שר sar
of the world, the officer of the world said this verse. When
did this happen?
Where were we? בשעה שאמר הקדוש ברוך הוא למיניהו באילנות. be-sha'ah she-amar
Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu le-mineihu ba-ilanot. When God made the trees and said
that all the trees come out according to their kind, נשאו דשאים
קל וחומר בעצמן. nas'u desha'im kal vachomer be-atzman. So the grasses or
the vegetation made their own קל וחומר. kal vachomer. And they said
the following: רצונו של הקדוש ברוך הוא בערבוביא, retzono shel Ha-Kadosh Baruch
Hu be-irbuvya, if God really was okay with things being mixed up
for us, the grasses... and the vegetation, למה אמר למיניהו באילנות, lama
amar le-mineihu ba-ilanot,
why does He demand that the trees be each one according to
their kind? ועוד, Ve-od, and in addition, קל וחומר, kal va-chomer, we
can make a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. ומה אילנות שאין דרכן לצאת
בערבוביא, u-mah ilanot she-ein darchan latzet be-irvuvya, trees normally are not commingled,
right? because trees there's space between trees normally, so they're not as
commingled as the weeds and vegetation is. ואמר הקדוש ברוך הוא למיניהו,
ve-amar Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu le-mineihu, and God still insisted that each one
be according to its own kind, that the different types of trees
don't be mixed up, apple trees here and orange trees there and
so on. אנו על אחת כמה וכמה, anu al achat kamma ve-chamma,
how much more so is this true by grasses and vegetations that
we really could create a sense of you know of confusion and
things being commingled, and if God cares about this by trees, He
should certainly care about it by us. מיד כל אחד ואחד יצא
למינו, Miyad kol echad ve-echad yatza le-mino, and therefore immediately each one
came out separated according to their kind. So this obviously picks up
on the previous theme that the creatures somehow were you know made
according to their desire. There was some sense of some spirit or
whatever it was that represented the creatures that were willing them you
know for to come forth and that agreed with the command you
know and and were part of the process of creation. So here
not only were they part of it, but they actually figured out
how they should have been created based on a קל וחומר. kal
va-chomer. פתח שר העולם ואמר, Patach sar ha-olam ve-amar, so the the
officer of the world opened up and said, יהי כבוד השם לעולם,
Yehi chevod Hashem le-olam, God's glory will be forever. ישמח השם במעשיו,
Yismach Hashem be-ma'asav, God is can be rejoiced with His creatures, that
God he could be so happy that His creatures made the you
know figured out on their own what God's will was, and that
even the the vegetation and the grasses came out according to their
kind. בעי רבינא, Ba'i Ravina, so Ravina asked, הרכיב שני דשאים זה
על גב זה, hirkiv shenei desha'im zeh al gav zeh, let's say
according to this מדרש, midrash, so before before we talked about mystical
creatures and פשט, pshat, so now we're going to talk about מדרש
midrash and פשט. pshat. According to this מדרש, midrash, what happens if
somebody grafts two types of grass or grass of vegetation? Now I
don't know how you would graft vegetation. תוספות Tosafot points out that
there is a sense of כלאים, kilayim, a forbidden mixture, when you
actually mix two different types of seeds, like you plant you know
wheat and barley together or two different types of you know vegetable
seeds together or so on. That we know. But the question is
what about if they were treated like trees and grafted? Would there
also be a sense of כלאים kilayim by them? I don't know
again how you would botanically do that. So רב חנינא בר פפא,
Rav Chanina bar Pappa, according to רב חנינא בר פפא, Rav Chanina
bar Pappa, מהו? mahu? what's the story? כיון דלא כתיב בהו למיניהו,
keivan de-lo ketiv behu le-mineihu, לא מחייב, lo mechayev, since it doesn't
say "according to their kind", so maybe you are not obligated because
the תורה Torah never insisted by them as much the sense of
separation of species. או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say, כיון
דהסכים ידיהו, keivan de-hiskim yadeihu, since God in the end was happy
with what they did, even though they weren't commanded to be according
to their kind, כמאן דכתיב בהו למיניהו, ke-man de-chtiv behu le-mineihu, it's
like they had been commanded. Now it's true when they came out,
they came out למיניהו, le-mineihu, but but maybe that was but that
since God had not insisted on it, maybe it does not create
an obligation to keep them separate in terms of our the way
we live our lives and in terms of הלכה. halacha.
They did it on their own.
But God agreed. But God never commanded it to be such. Okay,
now if you didn't have this מדרש, midrash, you don't even know
God agreed. Only this מדרש midrash you know God agreed because it
said ישמח השם במעשיו. Yismach Hashem be-ma'asav. So now that we know
that God was happy after the fact, does that create for us
a halakhic requirement to sustain this idea of separate creatures of separation?
כמאן דכתיב בהו למיניהו דמי? ke-man de-chtiv behu le-mineihu dami? and the
גמרא says תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Now this is quite fascinating,
not only because it's the use of מדרש midrash in הלכה, halacha,
but also it's the use maybe this is less interesting but I
think it's more so more, it's the use of the story of
מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit in הלכה. halacha. You know what we're sort
of doing is we're saying the way God wants the world to
work based on the narrative of מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit should inform
halakhic categories. Right, we how often do we ever do that? You
know we look at פסוקים pesukim and how the מצות mitzvot commanded
to inform the categories. But how often do we look at the
way it seems from מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit God wants the world
to work? Now obviously that works better by something like כלאים kilayim
because the whole idea of כלאים kilayim is a sense like you
know it does very much pick up on that theme of למיניהו
le-mineihu in מעשה בראשית. Ma'aseh Bereishit. God wants things to be separate,
you know each species according to its kind, and then later God
commands us don't mix kinds. So maybe we should look back to
מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit to determine what are the things that God
wants us to keep separate. So I find quite fascinating using both
מדרש midrash and the narrative and the story of מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh
Bereishit to you know without a פסוק pasuk, that links them to
inform a halakhic category. Now in one place תוספות Tosafot suggests that
maybe the emphasis is not so much about about grafting, because again
how do you exactly graft vegetables anyway?
and maybe it's more about the question about about שבע מצות בני
נח, sheva mitzvot benei Noach, because there is one opinion that שבע
מצות בני נח sheva mitzvot benei Noach includes the prohibition of כלאים.
kilayim. And that's actually learned from a פסוק, pasuk and the פסוק
pasuk there is את חקתי תשמרו. et chukkotai tishmoru. כי את חוקתי
חוקים שחקקתי לך כבר, ki et chukkotai chukkim she-chakakti lecha kevar, things
that have already been established from long ago, which is what was
Established long ago, that when God created the world, he wanted everything
to be למיניהו. lemineihu. So maybe the question here is in the
context of the שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach, would
that apply to vegetation as well? What makes that a lot nicer
is also besides number one avoiding the whole idea of grafting vegetation,
but what also makes it a lot nicer is is that then,
oh, so that makes a lot more sense that we're learning it
from מעשה בראשית, Maaseh Bereshis, because the whole idea of שבע מצוות
בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach almost taps into that sense of
natural order of things and going back
to the stories of creation. Whereas for a normal sort of הלכה
halacha context, drawing on the narrative of מעשה בראשית Maaseh Bereshis for
a normal מצווה mitzvah is something that is very strange. Okay, so
that is that מדרש, midrash, an interesting playing off of the tension
between the למיניהו lemineihu by vegetation as opposed to by the trees.
Now we continue. רב שמעון פזי רמי, Rav Shimon Pazi rami, רב
שמעון פזי Rav Shimon Pazi shows a contradiction. See, one פסוק pasuk
says ויעש אלוהים את שני המאורות הגדולים. Vayaas Elohim es shenei hameoros
hagedolim. This is a very famous מדרש. midrash. God made the two
large luminaries. כתיב, Kasiv, and it else says את המאור הגדול ואת
המאור הקטן, es hamaor hagadol ve'es hamaor hakaton, the big one and
the small one. So first he calls them both big and then
he calls one big and one small. So אמרה ירח לפני הקדוש
ברוך הוא, Amra yareiach lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so the moon said
to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam, Master of the universe,
אפשר לשני מלכים שישתמשו בכתר אחד, Efshar lishnei melachim sheyishtamshu bekeser echad,
is it possible two kings will use the same crown? Now I
have to tell you, I always thought it should be, is it
possible one king will use two crowns? Because when you hear the
word king, you think about God. So how could you equally use
both of us, both moon and the sun? But clearly that's not
what it's saying. The kings here are the sun and the moon
as well. And the reason presumably they're kings is because what does
the תורה Torah say the purpose of the sun and the moon
are?
ולמשול ביום ובלילה, Velimshol bayom uvalaila, to have dominion. So that's what
a king does, a king has dominion. So can
two kings use the same crown? Meaning, we can't have a partnership
kingship. The whole idea of kingship is one king. You can't have
two co-kings, that's never heard of before. Now, why would you have
two co-kings? Because the way the פסוק pasuk starts is it says,
God says יהי מאורות ברקיע השמים... Yehi meoros birkiya hashamayim... no, no,
what does the פסוק pasuk say? ויאמר אלוהים
יהי מאורות ברקיע השמים להאיר על הארץ. Vayomer Elohim yehi meoros birkiya
hashamayim lehair al ha'aretz. So they're both given the same responsibility, להאיר
על הארץ. lehair al ha'aretz. So you want them to be co-kings.
So it's only the next פסוק that says את המאור הגדול לממשלת
היום ואת המאור הקטן לממשלת הלילה. es hamaor hagadol lememsheles hayom ve'es
hamaor hakaton lememsheles halaila. He split their dominion in that once they
were called big and
small, after the aftermath of this story. But the initial idea would
be that they would be co-kings. So the moon says to God,
"God, ever hear of any idea of two co-kings? Impossible."
Interesting in the context of all these discussions with Rome, I mean
both the Greek Empire and the Roman Empire ended up after a
period of emperors or Caesars a triumvirate.
But very briefly for Rome, right? But they knew of it. But
maybe that was also the point, look how long that lasted. And
you know, so okay, so is it possible to have two co-kings?
So אמר לו, Amar lo, so God said back to the moon,
לכי ומעטי את עצמך, Lechi umaati es atzmech, okay, go make yourself
the smaller king, you'll be the subsidiary one, we'll give the primary
dominion to the sun. So אמרה לפניו, Amra lefanav, ריבונו של עולם,
Ribono shel olam, Master of the universe, הואיל ואמרתי לפניך דבר הגון
אמעיט את עצמי, Hoil ve'amarti lefanecha davar hagun amait es atzmi, because
I made a good point, I should be the one that
suffers? So אמר לה, Amar lah, לכי ומשלי ביום ובלילה, Lechi umishli
bayom uvalaila, don't worry, I'm going to give you dominion in the
day and the night, because you know sometimes you can see the
moon in the day. Of course it's a little ironic because the
whole point was to separate their dominions. But so is the God's
answer to this that we'll separate, one will be day and one
will be night? Or God's answer also that no, one will be
the real person in charge, the sun, which also makes sense because
the moon reflects the light of the sun. So you know, but
so God says, so that seems to be the point. Okay, the
sun is the real king, but you at least will be present
even during the day. You're
not going to be the BMOC, the big מאור maor on campus.
But anyway, but nevertheless, you'll be there during the daytime as well.
Did the מדרש midrash say it cried?
I don't know, let's keep on reading, I don't know about crying.
You said in the way that the daughter tested. The moon's testing.
Aha, so the moon's testing God. He gets punished, but not because
he tested God, not because he mocked him, he's questioning God's judgment.
God's judgment, that's interesting. Okay, so אמר לה, Amar lah, so the
moon said back to God, מאי רבותיה, what's the big deal that
I'm there at the day? דשרגא בטיהרא מאי אהני, Deshraga betihara mai
ahani, what good is a candle in the daytime? Big deal that
I'm around in the day, I don't have any, nobody cares about
the fact that you can see the moon in the day. So
אמר לה, Amar lah, no, God said back to the moon, זילו
לימנו בך ישראל ימים ושנים, Zilu limnu bach Yisrael yamim veshanim, oh
no, I'm going to give you a very important role. You're going
to be used for the way the Jewish calendar operates. You know,
the month operates according to you and so on. So, and 12
months make a year. אמר לה, Amar lah, so the moon said
back to God, יממא... Yemama... יומא נמי אי אפשר דלא מנו ביה
תקופותא. Yoma nami ee efshar d'lo manu bei tekufuta.
So note the sun still plays a role in the calendar. You
count seasons by it and the calendar is adjusted based on the
sun, right? דכתיב, well, you would think that at least that's good
enough, that at least it's the primary way in which the- in
which we count our- in which we count our calendar. But anyway,
the moon still wasn't happy because the sun still, you know, plays
a significant role even there. דכתיב והיו לאתת ולמועדים ולימים ושנים. de-chtiv
v'hayu l'otot u'l'moadim u'l'yamim v'shanim.
So the מועד moed is the seasons, that's the sun, and ימים
ושנים yamim v'shanim is the moon. And even there, notice that the
מועד moed is mentioned first. So anyway, the moon says, you know,
that doesn't- you really haven't made- given me anything better. So He
says, okay, זיל ליקרו צדיקי בשמך. Zil likru tzadikei bishmech.
So צדיקים tzadikim will call themselves after you. What does this mean?
יעקב הקטן, Yaakov HaKatan, שמואל הקטן, Shmuel HaKatan, דוד הקטן. David HaKatan.
Very often people are called the small one and that actually, sometimes
the greatest צדיקים tzadikim are called the small one. Now of course
one imagines, and the מהרש"א Maharsha tries to read this throughout the
story, that a subtext of this whole story, and I- you can
try to figure out how it's- plays out in all the particulars,
is the Jewish people as opposed to the other nations, right? Because
it's, you know, the other nations count their calendar by the sun,
the Jewish people by the moon. The moon is smaller, it's less,
you know, it- right, it shrinks, it grows, it's, you know, its
sort of success is not always, you know, it waxes and wanes
in terms of its success in this world. It's not in terms
of, you know, mostly it's at night, you know, if you would,
you know, maybe it's like has a lot of גלות, galus, it
doesn't usually, you know, have a lot of success in the daytime
except every now and then you can see the moon in the
daytime. But- but how- well,
it doesn't bring light to darkness, that's a nice point. But you
know, but how- but you could say how much good does it
do? Okay, so the Jewish people have a little success every now
and then in this world. What is it compared to the success
of all the other nations have, you know, in this world? That
there could be sort of that whole, you know, theme that is
going on here, and then of course, so they count themselves, you
know, so that's explicitly tied in here with the fact that the
Jewish people count themselves according to you. What? The sense of renewal,
right? Exactly.
Also, isn't there also a- a metaphor to humility?
So that's where I was going. So the last line that צדיקים
tzadikim call themselves in your name is this sense about being small
is actually, you know, a good thing. There's a sense about being
humble and not being so proud and arrogant and always whatever, you
know, and in the end, you'll get your reward. Is there- is
that being anything but that?
It kept on saying, "Is it not enough for me? Is it
not enough for me?
Is it enough for me?" Well, but you know, maybe that's giving
expression to the fact that the, you know, the Jewish people feel
like, "Is this fair?" You know, "Where is- you know, why is
it that we are always suffering? Why is it? You know, what-
you know, where is the- where is the fairness?" But the moon
still complained. I understand. Okay, so- the- so let's take a look.
חזיה דלא קא מיתבתבא דעתה. Chazyei d'lo ka mitvatva daatah. God saw
that the moon still was not happy, was not happy. Okay, yeah,
very nice. You know, okay, virtue is its own reward. Sometimes I'd
like some reward more than just the virtue.
Hashem is concerned about whether the moon is happy. Right! Right!
So- so let's see where this goes. So,
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, so God said, הביאו
כפרה עלי, Heviu kapara alay, famous מדרש, midrash, bring an atonement for
Me שמעטתי את הירח she'miateti et hayareiach that I have made the
moon shrink. והיינו דאמר ריש לקיש, V'hainu d'amar Reish Lakish, so that's
what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, מה נשתנה שעיר של ראש חודש
שנאמר בו לה'? Ma nishtana seir shel Rosh Chodesh s'ne'emar bo l'Hashem?
Why by ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh does it say that it's a
חטאת לה', chatat l'Hashem, a sin offering for God or literally to
God, but here we're reading for God? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar
HaKadosh Baruch Hu, שעיר זה, Seir zeh, this goat or that sin
offering that's brought on ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, יהא כפרה על שמעטתי
את הירח yehei kapara al she'miateti et hayareiach because I made the
moon shrink. So again, if you read this as a metaphor for
the Jewish people, what it could be is look, for the way
the world works, it is sometimes- you know, there are sometimes some
like necessary evils in order for a greater good to be served.
So yes, you can't have two kings. Yes, there has to be-
you know, the- the moon has to be smaller. But in the
end, is it fair? It's not fair, but it's a- it's necessary.
So sometimes even things that are done that are correct, there is
some, you know, the- some people can be hurt in the process
and some type of atonement if you would, or maybe there's a
better word than an atonement, reparation, you know, uh, needs to be
done. So in a way, that could be a nice metaphor, you
know, for the Jewish people, which is we just got off of
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and so on. You know, you know, כי
אתכם ידעתי מכל העמים על כן אפקד עליכם את כל עונותיכם. Ki
etchem yadati mikol ha'amim al ken efkod aleichem et kol avonoteichem. You
know, so we, you know, it's sometimes not always so great to
be chosen, but we, you know, we suffer as a result. And
in the end, it's like, you know, God acknowledges that yes, this-
there is bad things that came as a result of this. Don't
worry, I'm going to in the end make it up to you.
So I think that's like a way to see the metaphor of
this.
Yes, but it's more than that. It's saying God is guilty for
the
suffering and God
has- needs a כפרה. kapara.
Right, so, you know, right, so I was trying- you're right, you
are reading it- you are reading it literally. I was trying to
soften it a little bit because just- feels... Ideally to take that
to its full literal sense that God sinned was a harder concept
for me to get my head around. So I was rereading it
as God allowed it was a necessary evil and God is going
to make it up to us. But literally it's going even further
and it's saying that God sinned. It's sort of like the wonderful
story that they
tell in מדרש Midrash חסידי Chassidic story about that's a great ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah story where the חסיד, Chassid, whatever whoever it is,
the person goes before God and says, God,
I've done a lot of things wrong this year, I haven't always
got to מנין minyan and I wasn't always careful about this, I
wasn't careful of that. So it's true, I've sinned
greatly and I deserve to be punished. He says, but I have
to tell you God, I lost my
job, this happened wrong to me, my daughter got sick, there was
a pogrom in the town. I'll tell you what, let's just call
it even.
So that is I think a nice encapsulation of this idea. We
do wrong things but sometimes how do we feel about what happens
to us in life? So again, to me it's a little hard
to say take it literally, say God
sinned, but that is what the מדרש Midrash is saying.
Especially since God is responding to the moon's arrogance in the beginning.
I don't want to share with the sun.
Well, what about the flood? I mean, didn't השם Hashem acknowledge that
the flood was a mistake?
Well, he just said he wouldn't do it again. And how do
you read the words נחם nicham in the תורה Torah and are
those metaphoric? Look, it has a lot to do with questions here
about the degree of anthropomorphism going around and how much does that
sit well with your theology. But at least we could say like
this, at least we could say from the perspective of the human
experience, sometimes it seems as if God has sinned.
But yes, this is a very strong מדרש Midrash in terms of
that. So let's keep on going.
רב אשי רמי, Rav Ashi rami, Rav Ashi showed a contradiction.
ותוצא הארץ דשא, Vatotzei ha'aretz desha, it says that the grass came
out. That was on the third day.
וכל שיח השדה טרם יהיה בארץ, Vechol siach hasadeh terem yihyeh ba'aretz,
that the vegetation had not come forth because God wanted to create
man to pray and to work the ground. That's in the second
פרק perek of בראשית. Bereishit. So that means that the grass didn't
come out until after the sixth day, until after Adam was created.
במוצאי שבת, Bemotzei Shabbat, that was ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. So how
do you reconcile it? מלמד שיצאו דשאים, Melamed sheyatzu desha'im, so the
grass came, ועמדו על פתח קרקע, ve'amdu al petach karka, they were
right by
the lip of the ground, עד שבא אדם הראשון ובקש עליהם רחמים
וירדו גשמים וצמחו. ad sheba Adam HaRishon uvikesh aleihem rachamim veyardu geshamim
vetzamchu. So when they came out, they didn't literally come out or
they came out, a tiny tip of them came out of the
ground, and then it waited for Adam to pray and then for
them to grow.
ללמדך שהקדוש ברוך הוא מתאוה לתפלתן של צדיקים, Lelamedcha shehaKadosh Baruch Hu
mit'aveh litfilatan shel tzaddikim, God is desirous of the prayer of the
righteous and he wanted Adam, he wanted Adam to pray. רב נחמן
בר פפא הוי ליה ההיא גינתא, Rav Nachman bar Papa havi lei
ha'i ginasa, he had a garden, שדי ביה בזרוני, shadi bei bizruni,
he threw seeds in it, ולא צמח, v'lo tzamach, they did not
sprout, בעא רחמי, ba rachamei, he prayed, אתא מיטרא, ata mitra, the
rain came, וצמח, vetzamach, and they sprouted. היינו דרבי אסי, Hainu d'Rabbi
Assi, that's what Rabbi Assi says, God wants the prayer of the
righteous. Now what does that mean also, God wants the prayer of
the righteous? In the literal sense, some say also that that's
why the אמהות imahot started barren so that they would pray to
God and that God would respond. So it also makes God sound
also interestingly in the context of the whole previous story about making
a banquet for God, it's very anthropomorphic, like oh, I really like
when people pray to me, or it really is very meaningful in
terms of this religious experience.
Another explanation though, which again to me works a little bit more
theologically, was I think the מהרש"א Maharsha said it. He ties it
into another מדרש Midrash which is God initially wanted to create the
world with מדת הדין middat hadin because the first פרק perek of
בראשית Bereishit is all אלקים Elokim and then he realized that the
world could not exist without the מדה middah of compassion, of רחמים,
rachamim, and the second פרק perek of בראשית Bereishit says השם אלקים,
Hashem Elokim, which is also what it says here because
השם אלקים Hashem Elokim wanted man to come and then tend to
the garden. So he says that that's the idea of תפלה. tfillah.
The whole idea of תפלה tfillah is that the world should work
in a certain way based on its rules and based on laws
of justice, but God allows for prayer in order for there to
be greater compassion and something to override the laws of justice in
the world. So that's God sort of wanted to set up the
creation in that way, he desires the תפלה tfillah of the righteous
to show that, to set it up so that with almost being
a mechanism so that through prayer God could intervene in the world
and God could bring compassion to the world, and that's also very
much represented by the idea of rain. Rain is something that comes
from above and gives life to the world. So that God wanted
that to be an initial mechanism in the way the world was
set up.
As long as it's not a
hurricane and we don't want it. Right. Okay, look, it's all, I
guess we have to end. I'm really... Unless it's a hurricane and
we don't want it. Right, right. Okay look, it's already, I guess
we have to end. I'm really just alright but it's
okay. Thank you very much, you want to conclude with something? I
just want to say, I'm just looking at the source here. So
he says at the end of this bit that before the creation
of man there was no creation, it says the grass didn't grow
and that had to do with what רש"י Rashi says, that man
wasn't there to pray for the rain. And only when אדם Adam
came and he recognized the need for rain, then he prayed and
rain came and the grass grew. So I think that the point
is that man's connection to the world is through prayer. So if
we see something in the world that is missing, we shouldn't just
think oh, it's missing because God didn't give it to us. It's
missing so that we can ask for it. And when we ask
for it, then it comes and then that completes the connection between
us and God and the world. And so that's I think the
lesson of the rain. אמן, Amen, אמן. Amen. Thank you very much,
David. Thank you everyone for joining us. Have a good night.